A Guide to the Von Frieling's Salve Collection, circa 1500-1977, bulk 1900-1932
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Von Frieling's Salve Collection, circa 1500-1977, bulk 1900-1932
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-65
1 box with the dimensions of 5.5 inches x 10 inches x 15.5 inches, 1 folder with the dimensions of 8.5 inches by 14 inches, and 2 jars measuring 2 inches tall and 1.5 inches in diameter
University of Virginia
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated to the Claude Moore Health Sciences Library at the University of Virginia in 2010 by Chris VonFrieling. Prior to the creation of this finding aid in 2014, two items from the collection were processed into the Historical Collections artifacts collection in 2012.
Biographical/Historical Information
This collection includes an untitled work that supposedly belonged to Dr. Albert Von Frieling, a physician living in Soltau, Germany, in the early 16th century. No additional information could be found related to Dr. Von Frieling’s life or medical practice. Documentation written by Edward Colman and George Von Frieling that accompanies the book describes its discovery in approximately 1902 on the Von Frieling estate in Soltau, Germany. Colman and G. Von Frieling write that the book, which included an ancient recipe for green butter salve, was found inside an iron box with several decaying, unreadable papers. Their record dates the book to 1512, but this date lacks additional authentication and should be considered unconfirmed.
Much of the Von Frieling's Salve Collection pertains to the recipe for green butter salve, which supposedly was created by Dr. Albert Von Frieling in the 16th century. After the discovery of the untitled work on the estate in Soltau, Henry Von Frieling, a descendant of Dr. Albert Von Frieling, is said to have recreated the salve described by his ancestor. Heinrich (Henry) Von Frieling was born 21 September 1885 in Soltau, according to the inscription in the front of his notebook. He came to New York in the early 20th century, but little is know about his life, other than his business venture to market “Von Frieling’s Salve.” H. Von Frieling applied for a patent for the salve in 1911, and historical newspapers show that advertisements for Von Frieling’s Salve continued to run in several Iowa papers until at least 1931. An undated and unidentified newspaper clipping reports the filing of a bankruptcy petition for “Frieling Bros. (Henry’s Restaurant),” owned by "Henry V. and George V. Frieling" in the southern district, which possibly refers to the Southern District of New York.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of 17 folders. In addition to the untitled book, designated the "Von Frieling Sammelband," the collection contains photocopies of the book and materials related to the 20th century version of Von Frieling’s green butter salve, also called Von Frieling’s plaster salve. These materials include documentation and packaging for the salve, patent paperwork, correspondence, and various items related to herbal medicine and early German printing, as well as two samples of the salve itself.
The Von Frieling Sammelband is believed to have been owned by the Von Frieling family of Soltau, Germany. The book is a composite work in German with pages taken from at least three apparently separate works and sewn together into one bound volume. These texts include a work on the interpretation of dreams, another on the medicinal properties of various local waters, and other writings related to astrology and early medicine. In a description of the 20th century rediscovery of the Von Frieling Sammelband, the authors note that “this book contains quotations from philosophers of that period, notes upon the art of steel making and a formula for making a green butter salve that made Doctor Von Frieling famous as a man of healing power.” The book is bound in leather; the text is printed in Gothic-style German and includes small woodblock prints. Following the sections of printed text, the book includes an extensive section of handwritten notes, also in German, which appear to have been added by different hands and at various times up to the 1800s. Among the notes are several hand-drawn designs and sketches.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged by approximate chronology.
Contents List
- Von Frieling Sammelband, circa 1500-1800s, 1 leather bound book, 4 inches x 6 inches (Box-folder 1:1 [vault])
  Book is in poor condition; binding is very fragile and pages show substantial weather damage.
  Separated Materials Note
  Item stored in the Historical Collections vault due to age and physical condition.
- Notebook of Heinrich (Henry) Von Frieling, circa 1900-1912 (Box-folder 1:2)
  The notebook contains undated writings in German possibly written by Heinrich Von Frieling, and a short “History of the Henry Von Frieling Plaster Salve” written in English by Edward Colman and George Von Frieling and dated March 1912. The notebook also includes a newspaper clipping of bankruptcy proceedings in the southern district (perhaps referring to New York) which lists the entity “Frieling Bros. (Henry’s Restaurant)” owned by Henry V. and George V. Frieling as filing a petition for bankruptcy.
- Two jars of Von Frieling's Salve, circa 1911-1930s, Each jar measures 2 inches tall and 1.5 inches in diameter. (Box-folder 1:3 [artifacts collection])
  Instructions advise that the salve should be used "for cuts, boils, carbuncles, abscess and infection… for blood poisoning from shot wounds, snake, insect or animal bites and… for burns and scalds from water, grease, or acid."
  Items catalogued and stored with the artifacts collection under artifacts01301.
- Image of two jars of Von Frieling's Salve, undated (Box-folder 1:4)
- Product information for Von Frieling's Salve, circa 1911-1930s, 2 copies (Box-folder 1:5)
  Includes "History" and "Directions" for the salve, written in English and German.
- Original packaging for Von Frieling's Salve, circa 1911-1930s, Cardboard box 1.5 inches x 1.5 inches x 2.75 inches (Box-folder 1:6)
- United States Patent Application No. 641.062, signed by Henry Von Frieling, 1911 July 28, 1 original patent application, 2 photocopies of the application (Box-folder 1:7)
  Petition to the US Patent Office regarding Henry Von Frieling's salve.
- Von Frieling’s Green Salve ingredients list and preparation directions, undated, 1 page (Box-folder 1:8)
- Photocopies of pages from the Von Frieling Sammelband, undated, 5 pages (Box-folder 1:9)
- Correspondence of Henry Von Frieling, 1912-1932, 6 pages (Box-folder 1:10)
  Includes letters to Henry Von Frieling from E.A. Schmalz, Leo Kaulfuss, Thoralf Rosfjord, H. Koetter, Henry Isernhagen, and Ivan Clearwaters. Correspondence consists of testimonials and purchase requests for the Von Frieling salve. In English and German.
- Bound reproduction of the Von Frieling Sammelband, undated (Box-folder 1:11)
  Photocopied contents of the Von Frieling Sammelband
- Photocopies of pages from the Von Frieling Sammelband, undated (Box-folder 1:12)
- German cursive writing sample, undated (Box-folder 1:13)
  Writing sample of two different types of German script
- Kräuter Atlas of Johann Künzle, circa 1952-1975, 16 pages (Box-folder 1:14)
  Cover description: "100 heilpflanzen in naturgetreuer, farbiger Darstellung, ausgewählt, von Kräuterpfarrer Johann Künzle” (100 medicinal plants in lifelike, colored representation selected by “herbs priest” Johann Künzle)
  The atlas includes illustrations and written descriptions of 100 medicinal herbs, in German. Johann Künzle (1857-1945) was a Swiss Catholic priest and botanist known as a “Kräuterpfarrer” (herbs priest) for his knowledge of herbal medicine. He drew and collected medicinal herbs and promoted alternative medicine remedies and practices.
- Museum Guide from the Gutenberg Museum of the City of Mainz, English Edition, 1977, 51 pages (Box-folder 1:15)
  Short section on Early Printing in Germany on page 22
- Scenic postcards from Germany, undated, 2 postcards (Box-folder 1:16)
  Postcards depict Benediktinerkloster Ettal (Ettal Abbey, a Benedictine monastery in Ettal, Bavaria) and the city of Kufstein in Tyrol, Austria, with the Kaiser Mountains
- Donation List, undated, 1 TD (Box-folder 1:17)
  List of items that accompanied the Von Frieling donation